Good afternoon. Okay, so we've got the video working today. Today's דף
daf is דף ז, daf zayin, 7. We pick up at the
bottom of דף עמוד ב. daf amud bet. We're going through the
משנה, mishnah, the various types of business interactions you can't do. We
see that אביי Abaye says primarily what's forbidden are the types of
things that are מרויח, marvach, that gives them greater increase: lending them
money, lending them objects, etc. But that what's also forbidden is the
reverse: borrowing from them, making them pay up their debts, etc., because
it'll be a גזרה gozeira that it'll lead, you forbid that direction
because it'll lead to the other direction. But the primary problem is
transactions that'll give them
more resources. Whereas רבא Rava says they're both forbidden because of a
concern of אזל ומודה, azol umodeh, that as a result he'll be
happy and they'll give thanks. And רש"י Rashi pointed out the specific
issue of לא ישמע על פיך, lo yishamah al picha, that having
their thanks to their pagan god being through your agency and so
on. Okay, so that was the basic debate going through the or
the basic issue going through the whole list of things in the
משנה. mishnah. And then the third issue, as we mentioned, was a
specific concrete concern of לפני עור, lifnei iver, providing them the objects
of their worship. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, three lines, four
lines before the lines get the widest, at the two dots. רבי
יהודה אומר נפרעין מהן. Rabbi Yehuda omer nifra'in mehen. So this is
the issue about can you make them pay up a debt? So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can make them pay up a
debt because that's not even going to cause them any joy, that'll
cause them anguish. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, even though they're
upset now that they lost the money, eventually they'll be happy because
they actually got paid up the debt and the debt is no
longer riding on their back. So the גמרא Gemara says: ולית ליה
לרבי יהודה אף על פי שמצר עכשיו שמח הוא לאחר זמן? Veleit
lei leRabbi Yehuda af al pi shemetzar achshav sameach hu le'achar zman?
Does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda not agree with this logic that even
though it causes immediate pain, you look at the big picture and
in the big picture it's going to cause them joy? Where do
we see he holds this logic? By a very different case, not
relating to our interaction with the non-Jews, but the following. ותניא: Vetanya:
רבי יהודה אומר אשה לא תסוד במועד מפני שניוול הוא לה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer isha lo tasud bemoed mipnei she'nival hu lah. A woman
cannot put on like a type of a plaster on the face
for reddening the face or some other one, like these types of
mud masks or whatever it is on חול המועד Chol HaMoed because
it's disgusting. It will not lead to some benefit of חול המועד
Chol HaMoed and it actually just leads to something, it maybe is
a benefit for after חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, but not on חול
המועד Chol HaMoed itself and therefore it is an inappropriate type of
a way, you're supposed to look nice on חול המועד Chol HaMoed
and so on. So he says it's forbidden because it is a
disfiguring for her or, ניוול, nival, not disfiguring but some other whatever,
does not make her look nice, a de-beautifying for her. What's the
opposite of de-beautify? Anyway, ותניא, Vetanya, so the גמרא Gemara says: מודה
רבי יהודה בסיד שיכולה לקפלו במועד. Modeh Rabbi Yehuda b’sid sheyechola lekaflo
bemoed. However, he does agree by a type of a plaster that
can be peeled on חול המועד Chol HaMoed itself, שתפלו במועד shetefalo
bemoed that would be allowed. Why? אף על פי
שמצר עכשיו שמח היא לאחר זמן. Af al pi shemetzar achshav, sameach
hi le'achar zman. Even though right now it causes some anguish on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, she looks icky and disgusting and whatever, and
that's not appropriate for חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, but when she peels
it off she'll be very happy, she'll look nice. So anyway, you
don't have to focus on the micro, right now it causes some
immediate problems, in the big picture it's going to serve the ultimate
purpose, doing something on חול המועד Chol HaMoed that you look nice
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed and you feel happy on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. So here too, although it's a completely different case, it
just shows that he understands the concept that you don't have to
look in the micro, that you can look at the macro. So
why doesn't he do the same thing here? דאמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק הני דחול המועד דכולי עלמא מיצרי עכשיו סמיכי לאחר זמן. De'amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, hanei dechol hamoed dekulei alma meitzari achshav sameichi
le'achar zman. No, no, no, by חול המועד Chol HaMoed in general,
like anything we allowed on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, we allow me
to go ahead and cook and bake on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
Well, you know, I don't like cooking and baking, right? That's why
a lot of people, like I always have this fight with דבורה,
Devorah, like it comes to a יום טוב, Yom Tov, you have
to do all this preparing, I says, why are you preparing? Get
a couple of steaks, we'll make them on יום טוב Yom Tov
itself, right? So you know, have a fresh steak, whatever, you don't
have to get so worried. It's not שבת. Shabbos. But you know,
so some,
so why not just get it all done beforehand? But the point
is, okay, nevertheless even though there's some amount of effort that it
requires to be done on חול המועד Chol HaMoed itself, but it
leads to something that is you're happy about. So that's like the
big picture. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, right, רש"י Rashi
says: כל מה שהתירו לעשות במועד מיצר באותה שעה כגון שחיטה ותיקון
סעודה ויהיה ממיצר שמחה לאחר זמן שבתוך המועד. Kol mah sheheitiru la'asot
bemoed metzeir be'oto sha'ah, kegon shechita vetikkun seudah, veyihyeh mishemtzeir simcha le'achar
zman shebetoch hamoed. So any type of food preparation you're going to
do or anything you're going to do on חול המועד—I Chol HaMoed
mean, that's even
יום טוב Yom Tov itself anyway—it takes a little effort right now,
but we look at it big picture. So of course you agree
to the idea on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you look at stuff
big picture. But on the stuff about doing business with the non-Jews,
so maybe it's an area of הלכה halacha that fundamentally doesn't start
with the big picture look, it looks at the very micro. Another
way to look to talk about it is that maybe the non-Jew
will be happy afterward, but he won't be happy on his actual
holiday itself, right? I mean, חול המועד Chol HaMoed lasts a few
days, right? And that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said—I mean, the
גמרא Gemara isn't saying this—but if you can peel it off during
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, she'll be still happy during חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed. But if the non-Jew will only be sort of feel the
relief of having paid up his debt long- long picture, but not
in the next two, three days on his actual holiday. Okay, that's
a different point though. That sounds like the question is will the
timing work out, and that maybe the timing won't always work out.
The גמרא's Gemara point seems to be a bigger one, that in
general in חול המועד Chol HaMoed we always take a big picture
view, whereas here maybe we don't start fundamentally with the big picture,
we start with the micro, and that's why, you know, maybe he
disagrees here. Charlie, you had a question?
Oh yeah, no, Steinsaltz says that this stuff he's putting on is
lime, to remove hair.
Okay, right. Yeah.
No, I was just thinking like let's say it's a פיקדון pikadon
for something to give back to you, and should you try to
like, you know, based on this logic, you know, you might want
to say I try to like give it back to him later
so he doesn't get happy to get it back, I mean, you
know, be מוסר, moseir, oh thank god, because you know when you
lose something to someone, you can be כופר הכל, kofer hakol, like
you know I lost it, I this, I that, I mean you
know, this this doesn't come up here at all.
I understand. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, okay fine
we just did that.
רבינא אמר Ravina amar עובדי כוכבים ומזלות ovdei kochavim u'mazalot אימת יתירה
eimat yeteirah לעולם מיצר. leolam meitzar. No, so he takes a very
again negative view about non-Jews and he says רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda
point here is that he fundamentally doesn't agree that long-term they'll be
happy. He thinks that they'll always have wished that they could have
gotten out of it or found a way to get out of
it or something of that nature and therefore there won't be any
satisfaction even long-term in this case. All right, so מתניתין דלא כרבי
יהושע בן קרחה. Matnitin dela k'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. Anyway, that's the
position of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says you're
allowed to do it but חכמים Chachamim say no, you look big
picture and big picture there's שמחה simcha here as well. מתניתין דלא
כרבי יהושע בן קרחה. Matnitin dela k'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. And now,
the משנה's Mishnah not like רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Korcha. דתניא De'tanya רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
omer מלווה בשטר אין נפרעין מהן milveh b'shtar ein nifrain meihen
מלווה על פה נפרעין מהן milveh al peh nifrain meihen מפני שהוא
כמציל מידם. mipnei shehu k'matzil mi'yadam. That you're allowed to do it
if it's a debt that's actually
without a document you're allowed to do it because then you're always
afraid that they actually will find a way to get out of
it. So if there's documentation, then you have to wait, but if
there's not documentation, you have to seize the opportunity. And we discussed
that תוספות Tosafot פוסקים poskim like this. Obviously תוספות Tosafot was dealing
with a whole case where they were doing a lot of, you
know, lending with interest and so on and you didn't want to
lose the opportunity to get your debt collected, and תוספות Tosafot actually
rules that you're even allowed to do it like even with a
שטר. shtar. Although that seems to be again against the, you know,
the position in this גמרא. Gemara. Even the most lenient position in
this גמרא Gemara only allows it without a שטר. shtar. Okay, but
anyway מפני שהוא כמציל מידם. mipnei shehu k'matzil mi'yadam.
יתיב רב יהודה אחורי דרב יבא. Yativ Rav Yehuda achorei d'Rav Yabba.
יתיב רב יבא קמיה דרב הונא. Yativ Rav Yabba kimei d'Rav Huna.
רב יבא Rav Yabba was in front of רב הונא. Rav Huna.
יתיב וקאמר. Yativ ve'ka'amar. רב הונא Rav Huna was sitting and saying
הלכה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה. Halacha k'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. We rule
like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha
that you're allowed to collect debts if there's no שטר shtar because
ultimately you have to protect your own losses and you know interest,
even if it's a concern here of what do you call it,
of מיתי ומסור, meiti u'masur, even if it's a concern that they
might be happy. והלכה כרב יהודה. Ve'halacha k'Rav Yehuda.
And we rule like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. הלכה כרבי יהושע בן
קרחה הדרנא. Halacha k'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha hadrana. So we rule like
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha like we just said,
that you're allowed to collect the debt. You know, maybe also an
additional factor here is is that because it's מיתי ומסור meiti u'masur
there's even less of an issue of שמחה. simcha. Maybe, you know,
they would have felt like oh my gosh I really could have
gotten out of that. Okay, so anyway but we allow it and
here's already you know we've already mentioned earlier the issue of איבה,
eivah, concern of hatred might be a factor that allows you to
do this type of business. And here we're having another concern that
even though you shouldn't be doing this type of business, maybe you're
allowed to do it if it's to protect your assets. Okay, so
we rule like that, that you're allowed to collect with a debt
on from you know before their holidays if it's if there's no
documentation. And כרב יהודה k'Rav Yehuda and we also rule like רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דתניא, De'tanya, this does not relate to our הלכה
halacha but it's just that this was the teaching he was giving.
Here's two cases where it's a seemingly a דעת יחיד, daat yachid,
right, a not a majority opinion, and nevertheless we rule like it.
One is רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha and the
other is like רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דתניא, De'tanya, תנא ברייתא. tana
Baraita. הנותן צמר לצבע לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור שחור וצבעו אדום.
Hanotein tzemar l'tzava l'tzboa lo adom u'tzvao shachor shachor u'tzvao adom. You
give your wool to a dyer to dye black and he does
red or red and he does black. So what's so you know
what's his liability? So רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו. Rebbi
Meir omer notein lo d'mei tzamro. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that
he winds up taking possession of the wool
and because he's like a גזלן, gazlan, he did something that you
had directed him to do and he actually changed the object, so
that effectively makes him a גזלן. gazlan. So as a גזלן gazlan
he winds up having stolen and and effectively taken possession of your
wool, so he reimburses you for your wool. Okay, which might not
be what you want out of this situation.
Okay, רב יהודה אומר, Rav Yehuda omer, now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says אם השבח יתר על היציאה נותן לו את היציאה ואם היציאה
יתירה על השבח נותן לו את השבח. im ha'shevach yeteir al ha'yetzia
notein lo et ha'yetzia ve'im ha'yetzia yeteirah al ha'shevach notein lo et
ha'shevach. No, he's not a גזלן, gazlan, he did it inadvertently. This
also had to deal with questions about whether שינוי, shinui, when you
make a change in an object, do you take possession of it?
And here you're not doing it with intent to possess, right, he's
just doing it because he's working for you but he inadvertently did
the wrong thing. So there's a lot of interesting בבא קמא Bava
Kamma types of questions here. Anyway, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
you don't really become a גזלן, gazlan, you don't really take possession
of it, it's still the original owner's wool. Okay, but now it's
the original owner's wool, but you did not do what the original
instructions. So what's the original owner's, so he owns the wool with
now the black dye but he wanted the red dye, what's his
obligation to you? So you do not have to pay what you
contractually agreed. You contractually agreed that you'd pay a hundred dollars for
the job. You do not have to do that. Since he did
not follow your instructions, you have the upper hand. So what's your
upper hand? If the improvement on the you give him the lesser
of his expenses, not his fee, his expenses, right? If the contract
was a hundred dollars, but actually what it cost him in terms
of equipment or whatever and so on was fifty dollars, part of
the point is in terms of determining his expenses you also determine
like the labor expenses, you know, so where exactly do you draw
the line for, you know, when somebody's determining the labor expenses that's
usually where they fold in the profit. They also sometimes fold in
profit when they inflate the actual cost of the objects itself, of
the equipment itself. But anyway, so exactly drawing the line between like
the technical expenses and how much he normally would have charged. But
anyway, if he normally would have charged a hundred dollars, but you
determine his actual expenses even including labor was fifty, right, you cut
out any profit, so then you get to say so that was
worth fifty. Now how much did the wool improve? You know, if
it was red wool, you gave him the wool, you wanted it
to be red, he made it black, so, you know, maybe if
he'd done it red, maybe it would have been worth, I don't
know, a hundred twenty dollars. Now that he made it black, it's
only eighty dollars and you'd agreed on a fee of a hundred.
So now you pay him the lesser of the improvement, the increase
of cost of value, and his expenses. So if the expenses is
less, the expenses was fifty and the increase in cost in value
was eighty, you only pay him fifty. If however, you know, the
expenses was more than the increase in value, which maybe because he
really ruined it, because you told him to do one thing he
did the other, whatever, so his expenses even exceeded the increase in
value, so then you only pay him the increase in value. So
you as the owner have the upper hand. You certainly do not
pay him what you contracted with him to pay, and you only
pay him the lesser of what his expenses were or of what
the objects increased in value. That's the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. ואם השבח יתר על היציאה, Ve'im hashevach yater al hayetzia, if
the improvement, the value, is greater than the expense, נותן לו את
היציאה, noten lo et hayetzia, you give the expenses. ואם היציאה יתר
על השבח, Ve'im hayetzia yater al hashevach, and if the expenses are
greater than the improvement, נותן לו את השבח. noten lo et hashevach.
Okay, you give him the so that's a בבא קמא Bava Kama
discussion. Anyway, he says, so there we rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So אהדרינהו רב יוסף לאפיה. ahadrineh Rav Yosef le'apei. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef turned around his face, okay, because this was where
was רב יוסף Rav Yosef in this whole discussion? So רבינא Ravina
right, right, רבא Raba whatever it is, was sitting...
Yeah, what's the order of where people were sitting? Hold on. רב
יוסף מבאי.
Rav Yosef me'backei. רב יוסף Rav Yosef was sitting behind.
רב זביד
Rav
Zevid
was sitting in front of
and רב אבא Rav Abba was sitting in front of רב הונא.
Rav Huna. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef heard this פסק psak and
he turned his face around. Okay. בשלמא לרבי יהושע בן קרחה, Bishlama
leRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, I understand why you have to פסקן pasken
like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha that you're allowed
to get get paid on from, you know, before their holidays if
it's without a שטר. shtar. Why? איצטריך, itztrich, you need to tell
me. סלקא דעתך אמינא יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים, Salka daitach amina yachid
verabbim halacha kerabbim, because he's a single opinion, he's not the majority,
and therefore I understand why you have to tell me that we
rule in this case like the single opinion. קא משמע לן הלכה
כיחיד, Ka mashma lan halacha keyachid, so here we say we rule
like the individual opinion and not like the majority opinion. אלא הכא
רבי יהודה למה לי? Ela hacha Rabbi Yehuda lama li? Why does
why did he feel a need to tell us that the ruling
was like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? פשיטא, Pshita, of course we rule
like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דמחלוקת ואחר כך סתם הלכה כסתם, Demachloket
ve'achar kach stam halacha kestam, because this was a debate, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but it's a debate that
is followed by a סתם משנה, stam mishna, and of course we're
going to rule like the סתם משנה. stam mishna. What's the סתם
משנה stam mishna that rules like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? מחלוקת בבבא
קמא, Machloket beBava Kama, so the מחלוקת machloket here, the משנה mishna
we quoted about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
or was it a משנה? mishna? It says דתניא detanya but it
was תנן. tenan. It's a משנה mishna בבבא קמא. beBava Kama. That
was the debate. But then there's a סתם משנה stam mishna בבבא
מציעא. beBava Metzia. דתנן, Detnan, we teach in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia,
which comes after בבא קמא, Bava Kama, כל המשנה ידו על התחתונה,
kol hameshane yado al hatachtona,
anybody who changes from the instructions that the owner gave him, he
has the lower hand, the owner has the upper hand, and that
exactly means that the owner doesn't have to pay what was contracted.
He pays him either the lesser of the improvement or the expenses.
וכל החוזר בו ידו על התחתונה. Vechol hachozer bo yado al hatachtona.
Similarly, and that was the actual context in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia,
if workers back out, you know, of a contracted agreement or the
owner backs out, then the person who backs out has the lower
hand in terms of like, you know, who can force whom and
who has like, you know, who has
who can make more demands or in terms of once the contract
was broken. So the person who breaks the contract, who breaks the
agreement, he has he's in the disadvantaged position. So anyway, so you
see we've got a סתם משנה. stam mishna. So why did you
have to tell me we rule like רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Of
course we rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's a סתם משנה.
stam mishna. So he says, כדרב הונא. kederav Huna.
Why did רב הונא Rav Huna have to rule like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda if you had a סתם משנה? stam mishna? משום דאין
סדר למשנה, mishum de'ein seder lamishna,
because he says yeah, the משניות mishnayot don't appear necessarily in order.
You can't frame it as a debate followed by a by the
anonymous silent anonymous position because who knows, maybe the order was the
reverse. Maybe first it was the סתם stam and... and then it
was the debate. So the גמרא Gemara says משום דאין סדר למשנה
mishum d'ain seder laMishnah דאיכא למימר d'ika leima סתם תנא ברישא ואחר
כך מחלוקת. stam tana be'reisha ve'achar kach machlokes.
Maybe רבי, Rebbe, you know, even though it appears בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia appears after בבא קמא Bava Kamma that doesn't that order's not
necessarily significant. Maybe fundamentally, the first משנה mishnah that was taught was
the סתם stam and then although רבי Rebbe positioned it earlier in
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, he really said that he wanted the debate
idea to follow the סתם stam teaching and so leaves things as
an open debate and not necessarily to say that we rule like
the סתם. stam. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if
you say you can never know the order of the משנה, mishnah,
so the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי i hachi if that's true,
כל מחלוקת ואחר כך סתם kol machlokes ve'achar kach stam למימר דאין
סדר למשנה? leima d'ain seder laMishnah? So then what? We're throwing out
an idea that if you have a debate followed by a סתם
stam we go by the סתם? stam? You're saying oh there's no
such thing, we never know what the order is. So then you're
telling me that we that really that we never have any principles
about a debate followed by a סתם? stam? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, ורב הונא. ve'Rav Huna. So רב הונא Rav Huna would
say no, no, I don't mean that you never say it. כי
לא אמינה אין סדר, ki lo amina ain seder, when do we
say that you can't follow an order and you can't learn anything
from the fact that a debate is followed by a סתם. stam.
I'm sorry, when do we say, excuse me, that you do follow
an order and that if you have a סתם stam taught after
a debate you go by the סתם? stam? בחדא מסכתא. be'chada masechta.
If it's within one מסכת, masecht, if it's within one מסכת, masecht,
רבי Rebbe organized, you know, had some sequence of the משניות Mishnayos
within one מסכתא. masechta. So if in one מסכת masecht first he
teaches a debate and then later in that same מסכת masecht he
teaches one side of the one side of it as as the
anonymous voice and he doesn't even show express a dissenting opinion, his
intention is to tell you this was debated earlier but you should
know this is the opinion. So yes, רבי Rebbe will that's when
order matters when it's within one מסכת masecht and the סתם stam
that follows is telling you we rule like the
סתם. stam. בתרי
מסכתות אמינה. be'trei masechtos amina. But if it's in two separate מסכתות,
masechtos, so there's a logical progression within בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, there's
a logical progression within בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, but you know, you
can't you don't conceptually view it like בבא מציעא Bava Metzia follows
בבא קמא Bava Kamma and everything you learn in בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia presumes that you learned בבא קמא Bava Kamma beforehand. So if
there's a debate in בבא קמא Bava Kamma and a סתם stam
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that's not necessarily meant to be read
in that sequence. So the גמרא Gemara says ורב יוסף, ve'Rav Yosef,
and רב יוסף Rav Yosef would tell back say back to you
no, כולן נזיקין חדא מסכתא הוא. kulan Nezikin chada masechta hu. That
would be true if you would have I don't know, a debate
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma and a סתם משנה stam mishnah in
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, then I would agree you it's not significant.
You don't read it in a sequence of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
comes after בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. But within בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, that is one big
thirty-perek מסכתא masechta and even though we divide it into three, nevertheless
you can definitely infer something from a type of a sequence within
the all of the בבות. Bavos. Okay, so that's where anyway all
of this whole was a lot of effort about that nobody's really
debating the הלכה. halachah. Everybody agrees that you rule like רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda that you know, anybody who switches has the lower hand
and you know and anybody who retracts from a debate has the
lower hand. Anyway, everybody agrees to that, okay, that you rule like
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. The question is do you have to say
it explicitly or could you just have inferred it from the סתם
משנה? stam mishnah? So one opinion says you could not have inferred
it from the סתם משנה stam mishnah because between בבא קמא Bava
Kamma and בבא מציעא Bava Metzia you cannot read a significance into
the sequence. And therefore we had to say explicitly we rule like
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. And the other said no, you can read
significance into it. Just one more line and then I'll take questions.
ואיבעית אימא, ve'ibayis aima, if you want I'll tell you that the
issue here is not that you read בבא קמא Bava Kamma and
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia in some type of a sequence. That maybe
maybe we don't. Maybe those are considered two מסכתות, masechtos, so you
can't infer something from which came first, the debate or the סתם.
stam. But here's why it should have been obvious we rule like
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. משום דקתני לגבי הלכתא פסיקתא, mishum d'katani legabi
hilchta pesikta,
because the ruling is ruled in the middle of some very like
like הלכתא פסיקתא, hilchta pesikta, like some absolute you know sort of
terse absolute
apodictic is the word they would use in the university, like just
here's the rule. You know, it's sort of said in a way
that is sort of said like this should you know the framing
is such that it makes this clear that this is the consensus
absolute rule. Because look at the way that it's presented. כל המשנה
ידו על התחתונה, kol hamishaneh yado al hatachtonah, כל החוזר בו ידו
על התחתונה, kol hachozer bo yado al hatachtonah, right?
It's sort of said like it's like this nice nice tight legal
principle, right? So the way it's framed makes it clear like this
is the rule, right? It's not sort of in a more discursive
way, oh, if this happens, what should you do? He says this,
he says this. You know, it's said in this very sort of
terse clear. So what?
How does it usually say?
Well, it's said in a כלל klal way. It's not said if
somebody gives the die or whatever, the ruling is X. No. כל
המשנה ידו על התחתונה kol hamishaneh yado al hatachtonah is a כלל.
klal. If like this is it's stated as a very like absolute
legal principle. רש"י Rashi adds also the fact that the principle that
issue about כל המשנה ידו על התחתונה kol hamishaneh yado al hatachtonah
wasn't the topic in
that משנה mishnah in
בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. Follow the agreement, you know, etc., makes it
clear that the only reason they were saying it was to tell
it to you as a type of a הלכה פסוקה. halacha psuka.
To tell it to you as an absolute rule. So רש״י Rashi
points out the fact that it was sort of שלעפט schlepped in
and not of the topic, but תוספות, Tosafot, I think if you
look at תוספות, Tosafot, משום דקתני
כהלכתא פסיקתא, mishum de'katni ke'halchata psicta, תוספות Tosafot says, כלומר מדקתני כל
המשנה הוא לשון הלכה פסוקה. klomar midekatni kol hamishane hu lashon halacha
psuka. So רש״י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, it's not because it wasn't
the topic so clearly it proves that it would be פסק paskened
that way. It's the framing. It's framed as a כלל. klal. It's
not framed as a case study: in the following case, what would
be the הלכה? halacha? It's framed as a principle, and the language
of a principle makes it clear that we פסק pasken like it.
Okay, there were some questions. Jenny, you had a question before?
I just was two inches away from the כל הנזיקין. Kol ha'nezikin.
Okay, thank you.
Yes, I had a question. Is there any opinion that says that
a person who ruins the product has to replace it with the
required, what would be the requested one that the person originally requested?
No, I mean you're right like if you say according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that you have to pay for the wool, so
you have to replace the wool and then the guy could sort
of after you've replaced the wool he could contract with you again
to do it again, you know, but right, but no, but nobody
actually says that you have to buy the wool and give him
what he was sort of, you know, asking. Maybe the guy doesn't
want to trust him again to give him what he was, I
don't know.
Just gives him the material back according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Right, exactly. All right. Okay. So anyway, so that was like a
little bit of a digression because we rule like רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha about, what do you call it, about
that you can do business with the, you can collect payment of
a debt if there's no שטר. shtar. So we had to say
we rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. And
as I reminded you, תוספות Tosafot actually winds up ruling you can
do it even with a שטר. shtar. He says that maybe the
גמרא Gemara was talking about a case where the Jews had the
upper hand. I don't know which universe תוספות Tosafot was living with
in that either in בבל Bavel or in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
the Jews had the upper hand, but he uses it as a,
you know, they had sort of control over the government, but he
uses it as a basis of saying nowadays where we don't control
the government and the non-Jews control the government, then even if it's
a מלווה בשטר, milva bishtar, we have to protect our assets and
therefore we can collect even on the, on the, you know, on
the holiday itself. Obviously, it's a hard to argue that their reality
was that much different than the גמרא'ס, Gemara's, but you know, but
obviously, it's like a number of תוספות'ס Tosafot's that we've seen and
will continue to see try to defend common practice and also defend
protect Jewish economic interests.
Didn't he also say the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi?
Yeah, that's correct. So anyway, so that's the question about ruling like
רבי—ruling Rabbi that you are allowed to collect the debt like רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, if it's—there's no שטר. shtar.
And now we're going to go to a couple of rulings like
רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha which have nothing to
do with our topic, but just are like הלכה כרבי יהושע בן
קרחה, hilchata keRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, like cases where we have where
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says more of a
single opinion and we—and we rule like him. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
we taught: לא יאמר אדם לחבירו הנראה שתעמוד עמי לערב. Lo yomar
adam lachaveiro hani're sheta'amod imi la'erev. Don't say to somebody on שבת:
Shabbat: oh, do you think that you might be able to find
some time to, you know,
to come by my
place, מוצאי שבת? motza'ei Shabbat? And the implication of course is like
I've got a job for you to do. You know, Jenna there
is a plumber and I've been telling her about my backed-up toilet
and I say, Jenna, you think you might be able to drop
by after שבת? Shabbat? And then she says sure, I can drop
by. You know, we never said to actually fix my toilet, right?
We just—I just said, do you think you could drop by? But
we all understood what it meant. Is that allowed or is that
considered like talking weekday talk on שבת? Shabbat? Because the actual words
weren't explicit, but it was sort of clear what we meant. Okay,
so the ברייתא braisa says you're not allowed to say it. רבי
יהושע בן קרחה אומר אומר אדם לחבירו הנראה שתעמוד עמי לערב. Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha omer omer adam lachaveiro hani're sheta'amod imi la'erev. No,
you're allowed to say it. You're allowed to say, do you think
you could come drop by after שבת Shabbat even though it's understood
what you meant. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה
כרבי יהושע בן קרחה. Amar Rabbah bar bar Channah amar Rabbi Yochanan
halacha keRabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. We rule that way. Oh, very good.
אמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה—we halacha just did. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan: Now here's another
one, which is a little bit more interesting and broader application, very
much about like halachic, about principles of פסק. psak. תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan. הנשאל לחכם וטימא לא ישאל לחכם ויטהר. Hanishal lachacham vetimei lo
yishal lachacham veyitaher. If somebody asks a sage for a ruling and
he says if this is טמא, tamei, impure, this is forbidden, don't
go ahead and try to ask another sage and try to get
a second opinion. Okay, so this is a really interesting question. Why
is it that you are bound by the ruling that you actually
get from the first, from the first rabbi or the first sage?
Is it somehow when a rabbi gives a ruling it creates almost
like a metaphysical reality that if I say it's אסור, assur, that
just that makes it אסור, assur, whatever—like it's not like there's an
objective הלכה halacha on the books, you know? Because of the principle
that there are multiple ways to read הלכה halacha and so on,
maybe if I'm authorized to give פסק, psak, whatever authorizes me to
give פסק, psak, that creates the reality. And therefore if I've made
it—it's אסור, assur, assuming that it works within the range of possibilities,
not if I say something completely, you know, completely off the reservation.
And therefore somebody else would therefore go ahead and negate something that
had already become a type of a concretized reality. הלכה halacha. *halacha*,
that's one way that some of the ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim* understand it.
Other way is more just an issue of כבוד חכם chacham, *kvod
chacham*, right? That if I've ruled that way and now you're going
to go ask somebody else, you are, that's disrespectful to me. You
asked me for a ruling. One of the נפקא מינה *nafka minas*
is about what if I say that it's מותר mutar *mutar*? Can
you go to somebody else and they'll tell you that it's אסור
asur. *assur*? Okay, you know, so if it's that I created a
metaphysical reality, I'm making it forbidden by ruling that it's forbidden, then
you know, then that's then it's only a problem when I rule
it's forbidden. If I rule permitted, I haven't created any איסור *issur*,
and then you could go to somebody else. If the issue however
is כבוד חכם chacham *kvod chacham*, then you shouldn't be able to
go to somebody else. I still remember like many years ago somebody
told me, I'm visiting my parents or whatever, they don't keep כשרות
kashrus *kashrus*, can I go ahead and eat their salad? And there'll
be, you know, there'll be cut up onions in the salad or
whatever, you know, point about דבר חריף *davar charif* and knife or
whatever, and I say, yeah, you know, you could rely, whatever, there
are different שיטות shitos *shitos*, you don't have to worry, you can
go ahead and eat it with the onions. And then they come
back and said to me, you know, I asked this other rabbi
and he told me that it was אסור asur. *assur*. And I'm
like, you know what, I first of all, I could have told
you it was אסור assur, *assur* too, it's not a חידוש chiddush
*chiddush* to say it was אסור assur *assur*, right? You know, and
number one, why'd you ask the other rabbi? You asked me, I
told you it was מותר mutar *mutar*, I still think so. Anyway,
it's like, but anyway, okay, so that's like one interesting question. Is
that the issue, or is the issue anyway, so that's the question
of if you got a פסק psak. *psak* that it was מותר
*mutar*, are you allowed to go to somebody else? The other question
is if you actually like went to somebody else and you got
a different ruling, are you allowed to follow that other person? Right?
Or, you know, how much is this just an issue of כבוד
*kavod*, and it's not an issue of what actually defines הלכה halacha
*halacha*? That maybe you are allowed to follow the other person, you
know? Is it about creating, the first פסק psak. *psak* you got
created that halakhic reality? Then if you even if you went and
asked somebody else, maybe you still, you know, doesn't matter, you're still
bound by the first ruling. Which is why often, you know, I've
definitely gotten שאלות *shailos* where somebody will say, Rabbi, I'm not asking
you for a פסק *psak*, I want to know theoretically how would
you rule with the following, because they don't want to sort of
like feel bound by that. Yes, Charlie.
Yes, do any of the commentaries in this reference the famous אגדתא
*aggadata* when a certain תנא Tanna *tanna* asked about מר בר רב
אשי *Mar bin Ashi* that led to, yeah I don't know.
I mean, yeah there are definitely a lot of cases that get
brought in about this. Okay, so anyway,
okay,
then that's one issue. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* by the way has
another question. תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos*, I want to look at תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos*, because it's very interesting, you know, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* very much
believed the number of places where this comes up, there's two areas
where this comes up, these types of whatever statements come up in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. One is, you the שואל *shoel* can't like,
what's it called, forum shop. You can't go ahead and ask me
and then you don't like the answer ask somebody else. There's another
הלכה halacha *halacha* which is that if you asked me and I
know, I the חכם *chacham* know that somebody else פסק *paskened* for
you, I'm not allowed to rule to override the other rabbi's פסק
*psak*, right? That's sort of like,
you know, sort of what is it, courtesy, professional courtesy, you know,
I can't go ahead and I don't have the right. In both
places תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* is upset because the whole enterprise of תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos* is we argue everything out, and through arguing everything out
a greater truth emerge. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos* why shouldn't you ask
around and get everybody to argue and get a greater truth to
emerge as a result? So if you look at תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos*,
he says, הנשאל לחכם וטימא לא ישאל לחכם ויטהר *hanishal lechacham vetimmei
lo yishal lechacham veyitaher*. ואם תאמר *ve-im tomar*, he says, וכי לא
ישאל לחכמים *vechi lo yishal lechachamim*?
Ask as many people as you want! וידונו זה עם זה *ve-yidonu
zeh im zeh*, and they'll all argue with one another. אולי ישיבוהו
מדברו *ulai yeshivuhu midvaro*, and maybe if like you got a פסק
*psak* from me and you think I'm misguided, you should go around
and ask other people and invoke a discussion and they'll get me
to give up my position if my position is wrong. Right, why,
why should we buy into just you know, you know the more
of voices that are heard, the better. It's very nice like it
expresses a whole attitude of, you know, the whole enterprise of the
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, right? Especially because it was not just the way
they ask questions on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's a school of
hearing multiple voices, right? Multiple תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos*, multiple voices. ויש לומר
דאינו אסור assur, לשאול אם לא יודיעו כבר שאלתי לפלוני ואסר לי.
אבל אם אומר לו כבר שאלתי לפלוני חכם... מותר *ve-yesh lomar de-eino
assur lishol im lo yodi'o kvar she-sha'al li-peloni ve-asar li. Aval im
omar lo kvar sha'alti l-peloni chacham... mutar*. So Jenna comes and asks
me a שאלה shaila *shailo* and I give her a ruling and
then she goes over to Charlie, or no Charlie isn't a rabbi,
she goes over to who do you go to, Jenna?
You go to Rabbi Jeff. And you say to Rabbi Jeff,
you say, Rabbi Jeff, Rabbi Linzer said X, Y, and Z but
I think he made a big mistake, you know, what do you
see here's my question? So that's okay for her to ask because
then she is actually the effect, like the effect of that asking
is not just for her to get a personal פסק *psak* that's
different. The effect of that asking is bringing me into the conversation
with him effectively by mentioning my name. And then he's going to
say, what? He said what? Are you sure he heard you right?
And then he's going to go give me a phone call and
we're going to talk it out. Okay, so it's like very interesting,
right? If you're just going for your personal פסק *psak*, so you
don't say I didn't like that answer, I'm going to go to
somebody else and get a better answer, right? But if the p-
The point of going to somebody else is actually to clarify the
הלכה halacha and to get them in conversation, right? So then that
would be okay. Now if רבי Jeff still can't convince me I'm
wrong, Jenna might still be bound by my first ruling. Okay, that's
a different point but that doesn't mean she's forbidden to go and
try to open up the conversation. So there's different questions here about
when, under what situations will the ruling be revoked and reversed or
overridden, can she follow a different ruling. But following a different ruling
is different than asking somebody else and trying to clarify the issue.
All right, so very interesting. And then he goes on to discuss
similar scenarios about when am I allowed to overrule somebody else if
I was asked afterwards and so on. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara, says like this. רצה חכם יטהר ויתיב. ratzah chacham yetaher
v'yativ. היו שנים. hayu shnayim.
Now let's say somebody came with a
שאלה and I was standing there together with somebody else and somebody
said what's הלכה halacha and I said oh it's מותר and they
said no it's אסור. assur Anyway you got two answers at the
same time. Two Jews three opinions anyway. היו שנים אחד מטמא ואחד
מטהר אחד אוסר ואחד מתיר. hayu shnayim echad metameh v'echad metaher echad
oser v'echad matir. One's forbidden one's permitted
so you didn't go asking somebody else. There were two right there
and they were giving different opinions. What should you do? אם היה
אחד מהם גדול מחברו בחכמה ובמנין im hayah echad meihem gadol mei-chavero
be-chochma u-ve-minyan if one is greater in wisdom and number
I'll get back to that. הלכה כמותו halacha k'moto follow the greater
sage. ואם לאו v'im lav but if it's not clear who the
greater sage is הלכה אחר המחמיר halacha achar ha-machmir just play it
safe follow the stringent opinion. רבי יהושע בן קרחה אומר Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Korcha omer רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says
בשל תורה הלך אחר המחמיר בשל סופרים הלך אחר המיקל. be-shel torah
hilech achar ha-machmir be-shel soferim hilech achar ha-meikel. Okay
no if it's a biblical matter you gotta follow the more stringent
one. If it's a rabbinic matter actually the opposite follow the more
lenient one. Okay so this is a really important principle, the big
halakhic principle that ספק דאורייתא לחומרא ספק דרבנן לקולא. safek d'oraisa l'chumra
safek d'rabbanan l'kula.
Now normally what does ספק safek mean when we say there's a
Torah doubt and a Rabbinic doubt? One thing it could be is
a ספק מציאות safek metzius a ספק safek about the facts, right?
I don't know if this piece of meat is חזיר chazir or
not so it's a biblical issue I better play it safe. Okay
on the other
hand I don't know if this item is מוקצה muktzah something like
that and it's שבת Shabbos well okay it's a ספק safek but
it's a Rabbinic issue so you don't know if it's מוקצה muktzah
or not because you don't know whether it was the object that
was being set out to dry before שבת Shabbos or not something
or whatever you don't know about some of the facts you can
be lenient and assume it's not a problem, right? I don't know
if this piece of meat I'm מילכיג milchig and I don't know
if this thing here is פליישיג fleishig am I allowed to eat
it because I'm מילכיג milchig oh well that would be the opposite.
I'm פליישיג fleishig I don't know if this thing here is מילכיג
milchig am I allowed to eat it or not? Well that's only
a Rabbinic issue you can assume it's not מילכיג. milchig. Okay now
by the way in some of those cases obviously I'm just talking
very broad strokes. There's always the question about if the facts can
be easily determined, right? You can't necessarily be willfully
ignorant or if something can easily you know if you can easily
get to the bottom of it. The question always is what does
it mean easily determined? Like
nowadays the examples I was using with כשרות we live in a
world of הכשרים hechsherim and we think that it's always you know
you always can find out the facts you know call up the
OU hotline or I could call up the company and try to
get to a spokesperson and blah blah blah. Like how much does
that mean that the facts can easily be determined or not? Like
what's that stage of being able to know. But anyway but a
general principle that you go you're lenient by Rabbinic and you're strict
by Biblical is normally like the first round in which that's said
is about questions about the facts, determining the facts. The חידוש here
of רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha is it's a
way of פסקנינג paskening a debate of הלכה. You you know some
פוסקים poskim say it's מותר some say it's אסור. assur If it's
Rabbinic you can rely on the lenient opinions. We have that so
internalized in our way of doing הלכה that we don't always realize
that it wasn't so obvious. I mean my God imagine we hadn't
ruled like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha any halakhic
debate we would have always had to take the more stringent opinion.
You know half of the תשובות teshuvos of רב עובדיה יוסף Rav
Ovadia Yosef are based on the principle oh it's a debate it's
Rabbinic we'll follow the more lenient opinion. You know so this is
as you this is all sort of this ruling of רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, when there are multiple voices at
the same time he says you're allowed to just follow the more
lenient one for a Rabbinic matter. Now the other important principle here
is the way רמב"ם Rambam says it is you know here it
just says that there are two opinions. רמב"ם Rambam says the way
רמב"ם Rambam frames this is I think ואם אי אתה יודע להיכן
הדין נוטה v'im i attah yodea l'heichan ha-din noteh is I think
the language of רמב"ם Rambam meaning how much and this really is
a really important question about the role of a פוסק posek right?
It's how much
is let me find this in the רמב"ם Rambam I think doesn't
have that little letter. Oh here it is. ה'. heh.
א' ממרים ה'. aleph mamrim heh. Hold on a second I will
read you. How much you know different פוסקים poskim operate differently. Right
some פוסקים poskim basically the sense you get is that basically what
they're there is they're counting up the different שיטות they record you
know what everybody sort of has
said and they're just go and if they can line up enough
enough.
to פסקן pasken like them they will, or if they can say
it's a debate and it's דרבנן derabbanan we'll be lenient. Other פוסקים
poskim you read them and you feel like they're aware of what
other of what other פוסקים poskim said, but they're trying before they
just start counting up the, you know, weighing the different positions, you
know, weighing the different numbers, how many on this side of the
scale, how many on that, they're actually trying to figure out what
they think the הלכה is that emerges from the sources. Right? You
don't just start by counting up the numbers on each side. So
if you take a look at רמב"ם, Rambam, רמב"ם'ס Rambam's language is
that second one. רמב"ם Rambam says the following: שני חכמים או שני
בתי דינים שנחלקו שלא בזמן הסנהדרין, Shenei chachamim o shenei battei dinin
shenechleku shelo bizman haSanhedrin, right, there's no סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
there's no central court to decide. או עד שלא היה דבר ברור
להם O ad shelo hayah davar barur lahem or it hasn't yet
come up to the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. בין בזמן אחד בין בזה אחר
זה, Bein bizman echad bein bezeh achar zeh, אחד מטהר ואחד מטמא,
echad metaher ve-echad metame, אחד אוסר ואחד מתיר. echad oser ve-echad mattir.
אם אין אתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה, Im ein atta yodea lehachan
haddin noteh, if you yourself don't know, can't like don't have
a sense of which way you think is the right way, all
you have are the different opinions, you yourself can't actually cast a
deciding vote based on your own assessment of the facts, then בשל
תורה הלך אחר המחמיר ובשל סופרים הלך אחר המיקל. beshel Torah halach
achar hamachmir uveshel soferim halach achar hammekel.
So that's really interesting in terms of in general in terms of
thinking about what a פוסק posek thinks, you know, his job is.
Is his job basically to tabulate and then just line up enough
positions and say we can rely on it, you know, assuming, you
know, or is the job let's look at the original sources and
decide actually which position makes the most sense. So רמב"ם Rambam says
you only return to go to this rule when you can't figure
it out yourself. The other interesting thing here is, is what does
it mean if היה אחד מהם גדול מחברו בחכמה ובמנין? hayah echad
mehem gadol mechaveiro bechochmah uveminyan? One has greater in terms of number.
What does number mean? Like if you're talking about one חכם, how
can one חכם be one, what's the number, bigger in number?
I know, so thank you, I hope that was not... it's okay,
it's alright. So there's so, so some say it means how old
they are, some say it means why, you know, that's an interesting
deferring to age. Some say it means actually how many תלמידים talmidim
they have, in terms of how, or you know, how far is
their reach. I don't know if it's normally said, the normal explanation
the ראשונים Rishonim give is number of תלמידים, talmidim, but a variation
that I could sort of suggest is how big is their community?
How many people rely, you know, follow their ruling? Maybe that's what
it means by תלמידים, talmidim, but תלמידים talmidim is a little different,
תלמידים talmidim is like how many disciples as opposed to you know
how many people turn to me as for פסק. So that also
becomes an interesting question before you get to oh it's a דאורייתא
de-Oraita דרבנן de-rabbanan let's be מיקל mekel let's be מחמיר. machmir. Even
if you're just doing the tabulating, how do you tabulate? Right, like
רמב"ם Rambam versus some obscure ראשון, Rishon, right, those not one and
one. Obviously רמב"ם Rambam carries a lot more weight, right? So how
do you do those types of tabulations? Right, the other interesting question
is, is about how do you tabulate in terms of like, like
you know, this is almost like the opposite of the question about
number of תלמידים. talmidim. If like, you know, תוספות says something and
then all of the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, Ashkenazi פוסקים poskim follow תוספות, is
that twenty votes or one vote on that side? Because they're all
just you know, they're all just going to repeat what תוספות says.
Not always, not always like just mimicking it. Anyway, so these are
really interesting questions in terms of what do you use to, how
much do you do a tabulating and a weighing, or how much
do you follow, you know, that's the issue about if one is
גדול מחברו, gadol mechaveiro, that's the weighing and the tabulating. How much
do you say no, דאורייתא de-Oraita we're strict, דרבנן de-rabbanan we're מיקל,
mekel, but also still that's within a world of tabulating and not
deciding. It's just determining it based on דאורייתא de-Oraita דרבנן. de-rabbanan. And
how much do you do it based on I'm going to first
figure it out and I'm only going to go to those rules
if I can't figure it out for myself. So one minute, so
let's just finish. So obviously where this is leading is that we
go like רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. which is
a good thing. אמר רב יוסף הלכה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה. Amar
Rav Yosef halacha ke-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. We rule like רבי יהושע
בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. Okay, one final issue that comes
up interestingly is if you look at תוספות בשל תורה הלך אחר
המחמיר. beshel Torah halach achar hamachmir.
So תוספות says רש"י היה פוסק בכל איכא דאמרי שבבתלמוד בשל תורה
הלך אחר המחמיר ובשל סופרים הלך אחר המיקל. Rashi hayah posek bechol
ika de-amrei shebattalmud beshel Torah halach achar hamachmir uveshel soferim halach achar
hammekel. When
the גמרא Gemara has two languages, right, two versions of a debate.
איכא דאמרי Ika de-amrei the
position was the following way. So that's always a question. Which of
those two versions do you go by? Okay, so he says how
much you treat that as two חכמים chachamim that are arguing when
there's an איכא דאמרי ika de-amrei in the גמרא, a different version
of the same debate. Okay? So רש"י Rashi sort of treated that
as, well, if it's a תורה Torah matter we'll always follow the
strict one, but if it's a rabbinic matter not we go by
the lenient one, we go by the latter position. Okay, וריב"א פירש
דכל היכא דאיכא דאמרי לגבי לשון ראשון כטפל לעיקר והלכתא כלשון קמא.
ve-Riba peresh dechol heicha de-ika de-amrei legabbei lashon rishon ketafel le-ikkar vehilcheta
kelashon kamma. We always go by the first
opinion. So רש"י Rashi assumes the default of an איכא דאמרי ika
de-amrei where there's more weight in the second version of the debate
and תוספות says the other position is there's more weight in the
first version of the debate. And then the third possibility is רבנו
תם פירש בדאורייתא לחומרא ובדרבנן לקולא. Rabbeinu Tam peresh bede-Oraita lechumra uviderabbanan
lekula.
So fascinating how they're all over the map in terms of how
you deal with not when there's a debate
of
opinion. Yeah Charlie, you had a question.
Yes, so there must be times when you feel like you really
gotta פסקן pasken leniently for someone. When can you pull out the
obscure שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch that everybody else ignores?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So I mean whatever. Those are other principles in
terms of פסק. כדאי הוא Kedai hu so-and-so לסמוך עליו lismoch alav
בשעת הדחק. b'sha'as hadechak. So
yeah, there are a lot of, right, I mean this is obviously
just some broad rules. Okay, so the ברייתא baraita says like this.
תנו רבנן. וכולן שחזרו בהן, V'kulan shechazru bahen, it's another הלכה of
רבי יהושע בן קרחה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. All of they who
reverted, אין מקבלין אותם עולמית, ain mikablin osam olamis, forever.
Now who is they who returned? So רש"י Rashi says it means
a גזלן gazlan wants to, you know, admit that he was a
גזלן gazlan and wants to be re-accepted into the community and trusted
again. That raises a lot of interesting questions, right? How much does
principles about תשובה teshuvah and the sense that we believe that God
will forgive you mean the same as restoring trust of the community?
It's all very nice God will forgive you, God knows what's in
your heart, and anyway, you know, that's about forgiveness. Forgiveness is a
little different than trust. Okay and, you know, הלכה generally is very
sort of, you know, pragmatic and understands it's all very nice to
speak theologically about תשובה. teshuvah. If we want to start trusting you
again, you have to win our trust. So that's part of this
question here. תוספות reads this, I'm going to follow תוספות'ס Tosfos's read
of this because the circumstances matter what we think we're talking about.
תוספות reads it as the following case. It's not a question of
trust, like can I trust you to, I don't know, sell me,
you know, כשר kosher food or whatever, or trust you to leave
my kids with you, you know, all these like very obviously cases
we deal with in sadly in contemporary society, just the whole story
came out in the Jewish Week, I don't know if people were
reading about this case in Baltimore. Anyway, the question is is that
it's a question about like following the laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. Here's somebody who was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz and they
decided that they were going to work to be a חבר, chaver,
somebody who they could be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות, mafrish trumos u'ma'asros, be
trusted in טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. And they went ahead and then
they חזרו. chazru. Then they reverted back to their old ways and
to being sloppy about it. And now they say I want you
to accept me back to be able to be someone who could
be trusted with, you know, with תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros and טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'taharah and so on. Can we, once they've seen that
they are, you know, that they have reverted and that, you know,
they slipped back, can we trust them now to, you know, once
again? That's the question. So וכולן שחזרו בהן, v'kulan shechazru bahen, so
תוספות reads חזרו chazru means they reverted back to their sloppy
ways, okay? אין מקבלין אותם עולמית, Ain mikablin osam olamis, דברי מאיר.
divrei Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you never will re-accept them.
Now you see that they really can't hold on to, you know,
maybe they're trying to be sincere or whatever, but they can't hold
on to it. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, חזרו בהן במטמוניות
אין מקבלין אותם, chazru bahen b'matmonyos ain mikablin osam, בפרהסיא מקבלין אותם.
b'farhesya mikablin osan. If they basically reverted in private but in public
they made it look like they were still being פרום, frum, okay,
then you certainly can't trust them. Because then they're just doing things
to trick people. Right? When they're caught in private not keeping it
but in public, you know, they keep it. Then, ach, you know,
then they're totally,
you know, they're just doing stuff for show and you can't trust
them. But if, maybe somewhat ironically, even in public they're no longer
keeping to it, so they're not trying to trick anyone. They just
weren't able to keep up to their commitments. Then we can trust
them if they came to, if they're now going to try again.
Okay, we allow them to try again as long as they weren't
trying to deceive anybody. איכא דאמרי, Ikka d'amri, some say עשו דבריהם
במטמוניות מקבלין אותם, asu divreihem b'matmonyos mikablin osam, בפרהסיא אין מקבלין אותם.
b'farhesya ain mikablin osam. If, no, if maybe this עשו דבריהם asu
divreihem as תוספות reads the meaning, if they were, if they kept,
if the first time around they were, we knew that they were
careful in their commitment and that they were keeping them even in
private when nobody else was looking in terms of their care of,
you know, תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'ma'asros, then even when they slipped, we'll
allow them to come back. Because we knew the first time around
they were careful to keep it in private. But if it's בפרהסיא,
b'farhesya, if we only knew the first time around what we saw
in public but we never the first time around saw their private
behavior and now they slipped, now we can't necessarily accept them back.
So different ways of determining, you know, somebody who's not a bad
person, right? They're brought up in a certain way with a lack
of care, they're trying to live up to a higher standard, they
slip. Do we assume that we can give them another chance? רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda basically says is I'm prepared to give them another
chance unless there's, you know, if I have enough reason to make
me feel like they might do it right the second time. But
if basically they seem to be deceiving or I never know that
they really did it right the first time, I'm not necessarily prepared
to trust them. Okay. רבי שמעון ורבי יהודה בן קרחה אומר, Rabbi
Shimon v'Rabbi Yehuda ben Korcha omer, and here's why we're quoting it
because רבי יהושע בן קרחה. בין כך ובין כך מקבלין. Ben kach
u'ben kach mikablin. It doesn't matter whether they kept it initially in
private or only in public,
whether when they were reverting they were still pretending to keep it
in private, etc. We always should be an open arm policy to
be prepared to accept people back. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as it says, שובו
בנים. shuvu banim. שובבים *shovavim*, return wayward children. אמר רבי יצחק איש
פרחא *amar Rabbi Yitzhak ish Parcha*, אמר רבי יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*,
הלכה כאותו הזוג *halacha k'oto hazug*, we rule like that pair, that
we always accept them back. But again, that’s interesting because as I
said, this comes up a lot in contexts
of people
convicted of crimes, and particularly it’s deeply disturbing when people are issues
about abuse and so on, and sexual abuse, and they say, "Oh,
I’ve done תשובה *teshuvah*, accept me back." Most of the time they
don’t even really say they’ve done תשובה *teshuvah*. "Mistakes were made" is
the type of תשובה *teshuvah* they give, or they say they’re sorry,
but then they don’t actually spend their money and efforts trying to
rectify the harm that they’ve done and really ask forgiveness of the
people that they’ve harmed. But even if they go through all of
that, the question still is: fine, but does that mean that we
should now just go ahead and trust you?
It’s all very nice, I hope you have done תשובה *teshuvah* and
I hope God forgives you. I’m not going to let you watch
my kid. So the question is also like what’s at stake, what’s
at risk? So even this position that says we accept them back,
it means the concern here is more of
a type of a question about to trust them with טומאה וטהרה
*tumah v'taharah* and so on, not like ritual stuff isn’t important, but
it’s still a little
different in terms of the purely ritual realm than in stuff that
really can bring injury to people. So it’s interesting, these, it’s a
very relevant type of a question, and in general הלכה *halacha*, like
for example in another case, somebody is known to have,
let’s say, they sell טרף *treif* meat because to make a higher
profit and they’re caught selling טרף *treif* meat. If they can get
up and say that they’ve done תשובה *teshuvah* and we’re not going
to trust him to buy our meat, this person again. Here also
the problem with just a question about sloppiness, somebody does stuff because
of a profit incentive, somebody does stuff to make money, somebody does
stuff because of their own character in terms of their
inability to control certain types of behaviors and so on, we have
to be more wary based on what those realities are. Anyway, so
this is very important in terms of that question about when do
we,
the first point about תשובה *teshuvah* is God will forgive you. When
does that mean we as a community trust you again?
That much, there the facts and the ability to restore trust is
not so obvious. And even though here רבי יהושע בן קרחה *Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Korcha* says we do accept the person, what's at stake
here is relatively minor as opposed to cases where what's at stake
is much larger in terms of people's safety and protection. So let's
just continue on to the next case. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, אומר
שלושה לפניהם ושלושה אחריהם אסור *Rabbi Yishmael omer shelosha lifneihem u-shelosha achareihem
asur*, three days before and three days after their holidays, not just
three days before is forbidden. וחכמים אומרים לפניהם אסור אחריהם מותר *v'chachamim
omrim lifneihem asur achareihem mutar*, only before is forbidden, after is permissible.
אמר רב תחליפא בר אבדימי אמר שמואל Shmuel *amar Rav Tachlifa bar
Avdimi amar Shmuel*, now again, we have here a censored text. The
original text says, לדברי רבי ישמעאל נוצרי לעולם אסור *l'divrei Rabbi Yishmael
Notzri l'olam asur*.
A Christian, it’s always forbidden to do business, because their holiday is
Sunday, three days before, three days after, you're never going to do
business with them.
And that’s significant as we said. Number one, it’s the one גמרא
*Gemara* that implicitly, pretty explicitly, but okay, implicitly basically it says that
Christianity is considered עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. And number although מאירי *Meiri*
reads נוצרי *Notzri* means people of נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar*, because מאירי *Meiri* doesn't
like the idea that Christianity is considered עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. And
number two, that even a holiday like a weekly holiday like Sunday
is a significant enough holiday for these הלכות *halachot*. וחכמים אומרים *v'chachamim
omrim*, and the sages say, לפניהם אסור אחריהם מותר *lifneihem asur achareihem
mutar*, only before is forbidden, after is permissible. So that seems to
just be reiterating what we said initially. So that's the גמרא *Gemara*'s
point. The גמרא *Gemara* doesn't like it that it's just reiterated. חכמים
היינו תנא קמא Tanna Kama *chachamim hainu tana kama*, isn't that the
original opinion that before is forbidden, after is permissible? הן ולא אידיהן
איכא בינייהו *hen velo edein ika beinyahu*. So now the גמרא *Gemara*
is going to use this opening, since it sounds like it’s just
repeating what we said before, to say a whole wide range
of possible debates maybe we’re going to squeeze into this opening about
why when the second sages say only before is the problem, how's
that different than the first
sages? Maybe they're debating some of these following details. Number one possibility
is, הן ולא אידיהן איכא בינייהו *hen velo edein ika beinyahu*, whether
when we say three, does three mean other than the holiday or
including the holiday? תנא קמא Tanna Kama סבר הן ולא אידיהן *tana
kama savar hen velo edein*, that’s what we said yesterday: three days
before not including the holiday, for a total of four days. ורבנן
בתראי verabbanan basrai, סברי הן ואידיהן *v'rabanan batrai savri hen v'edein*. The
later rabbis, since they just say לפניהם אסור *lifneihem asur*, it's a
more terse way, they mean three including the holiday, so it's two
plus the holiday. That's one way of explaining how the later opinion,
the second opinion, is different than the earlier one. איבעית אימא ibayaseima
*ibayit eima*, if you want I can say, נשא ונתן איכא בינייהו
*nasav v'natan ika beinyahu*. Another debate we had before: what is the
הלכה *halacha* after the fact if you did business on the period
before the holiday? On the holiday everybody agrees that the proceeds are
forbidden. What if you did business before the holiday? That's a debate.
תנא קמא Tanna Kama סבר נשא ונתן מותר *tana kama savar nasav
v'natan mutar*. The תנא קמא Tanna Kama *tana kama* says... It's only
that the act of doing business is forbidden, but afterwards the proceeds
are permissible. רבנן בתראי, Rabbanan Basrai, the later rabbis that just say
אסור, they don't say it's אסור to do business. They just say
it's אסור, so אסור in an unqualified way is going to be
read to mean even the proceeds that results from it are forbidden.
נסבא ונתנא אסור. nasava venasana assur. That's another way of saying what
they debate. So we've revisited two earlier discussions. איבעית אימא ibayaseima here's
a third way of saying the debate. דשמואל איכא בינייהו. deshmuel ika
beinaihu. They debate שמואל's Shmuel ruling. דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, very important
line here we're about to say, we'll repeat it in a few
days. Okay. בגולה, bagola, outside of the land of Israel אין אסור
אלא יום אידם. ein assur ella yom edam.
There's no idea three days before, the only thing that is forbidden
is the day of the holiday itself. Now why is that? Why
is out of Israel less forbidden than in Israel? So רש"י Rashi
says, well you know Israel makes everybody פרום-er. frum I'm a little
bit joking but it's more or less in Israel the Jews are
פרום-er, frum the non-Jews are פרום-er frum about their pagan religion. Out
of Israel you know non-Jews themselves aren't so פרום frum about their
pagan religion, so only the day of, not the day before, which
is like what, what does it have to do being in Israel
or out of Israel about how serious they are about their pagan
religion? So the other line that רש"י Rashi says is out of
Israel we have to more be concerned about our relationship with the
non-Jews. Now which is pretty funny cause in Israel although it was
our land but still the Romans had a pretty heavy hand of,
you know, ruling over us and concern about our interaction with the
Romans I don't think was any less than our concern with interaction
with the Babylonians. But anyway so it's a very bizarre
very bizarre this ruling which is certainly right for saying
something in the גמרא is bizarre, but anyway it's very bizarre this
ruling that somehow out of Israel it's less restriction as how we
deal with non-Jews.
But it is very relevant because based on this it gave ראשונים
a lot of latitude to say some of these restrictions will be
much weaker because we're dealing with non-Jews out of Israel and you
see based on שמואל Shmuel that non-Jews in Israel you have to
be much more separate, non-Jews out maybe less so. Again so it's
interesting to speculate where the heck this is coming from it's also
particularly interesting that שמואל Shmuel, of course is living out of Israel.
Okay. But anyway that's the ruling. בגולה bagola אין אסור אלא יום
אידם, ein assur ella yom edam, only the day itself. תנא Tanna
קמא אית ליה דשמואל, isle deshmuel, so the תנא קמא holds of
שמואל, Shmuel three days before will only apply out of Israel, and
רבנן בתראי, the later rabbis who just say אסור in a more
categorical way, we're going to read that as a broader prohibition. לית
להו דשמואל. lait lehu deshmuel. They would say that the prohibitions apply
equally in Israel and out of Israel. So that's a third way
again it just allows us to introduce שמואל Shmuel into this discourse,
it's hard to actually believe that that was what was being debated
but it allows us to introduce שמואל Shmuel into this discourse. And
finally איבעית אימא another thing they could be debating.
דנחום המדי איכא בינייהו. denachum hamada ika beinaihu. נחום המדי Nachum HaMada
the Median from Mede. דתניא detanya נחום המדי אומר Nachum HaMada omer
אינו אסור אלא יום אחד לפני אידיהן. eino assur ella yom echad
lifnei edeihen. Not three days before, only one day before. So because
remember the last תנא just says before is forbidden. They didn't say
the word three days in the משנה Mishnah we just read. So
תנא קמא our first תנא לית ליה דנחום המדי, lais lei denachum
hamada, he doesn't hold of it. He says explicitly three days before
you're not allowed to do business. ורבנן בתראי, the rabbis who argue
on רבי ישמעאל, they just say no only before not after. So
only before maybe they hold only one day before. אית ליה דנחום
המדי. isle denachum hamada. They hold of נחום המדי. Nachum HaMada. So
what we've done here is we've introduced again we tried to sort
of wedge it between the first תנא קמא and these rabbis but
whatever they're debating or not debating we've introduced two new ideas. Number
one is the idea of שמואל that the whole idea of three
days before only applies in Israel out of Israel it's only the
day itself and also a very lenient opinion of נחום המדי Nachum
HaMada that doesn't rejects the whole idea of three days before and
says it's only one day before. Okay so we will pick up
with this tomorrow.